Finding Aid for Edward Henry Kraus Papers, 1904-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Henry Kraus Papers 1904-1970
Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-
851645; Aa 2
Edward H. Kraus (1875-1973) was a Professor of Mineralogy at the University of Michigan and also served as Dean of the Summer Session, 1915-1933, Dean of the College of Pharmacy, 1923-1933, and Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1933-1945. The collection consists of correspondence, as well as speeches and other files related to his academic career and his association with the Ann Arbor First Methodist Church, the University Research Club, and Phi Kappa Phi fraternal organization.
4.25 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Professor Kraus (donor no. 2173 ) and from the Summer Session office (donor no. 1036 ). Additional materials were donated by John D. Kraus, Jr. (donor no. 7949 ).
The collection is open to research.
Edward H. Kraus was born in 1875 in Syracuse, NY to German parents. He earned his B.S. in 1896 and his M.S. in 1898, both from Syracuse University. He taught at Syracuse University for two years before going to Germany, where he studied mineralogy, geology, and chemistry at the University of Munich. He earned a Doctor of Philosophy in 1901, and returned to the Syracuse to teach mineralogy.
Kraus joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1904, where he stayed for the rest of his academic career. He was a Professor of Mineralogy and also served as Dean of the Summer Session, 1915-1933, Dean of the College of Pharmacy, 1923-1933, and Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1933-1945. He retired in 1945 from teaching but maintained an office at the university. He continued his research and publishing until 1970.
Edward Kraus was considered to be an international authority on crystallography and mineralogy. He was the author of five textbooks and numerous scientific papers on mineralogy and crystallography. He was also a founding member and first president of the Mineralogical Society of America in 1919.
He also served as president or chairman of many organizations on the national, state, and city levels and at the University of Michigan. These organizations had various focuses, including mineralogy, pharmacy, science in general, honor societies, and higher education.
Edward Kraus died in 1973 at the age of 97.
The Edward Kraus papers document his career as professor of mineralogy and administrator at the University of Michigan; his activities in professional organizations, including g the University Research Club and the Mineralogical Society of America; and his involvement with the Ann Arbor First Methodist Episcopal Church and the Wesley Society. The collection is divided into two series, Correspondence and Other Activities and Interests.
Subjects:
First Methodist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Methodist Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Phi Kappa Phi. University of Michigan chapter.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; University of Michigan. Research Club.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Mineralogical Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Religion.; University of Michigan. Summer Session.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Bragg, Lawrence Sir, 1890-1971.; Fermi, Enrico, 1901-1954.; Goudsmit, Samuel A. (Samuel Abraham), 1902-1978; Heisenberg, Werner, 1901-1976.; Laue, Max von, 1879-1960.; Pauli, Wolfgang, 1900-1958.; Sommerfeld, Arnold, 1868-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The majority of the Correspondence (1910-1933, 2 linear feet) series is letters written by Kraus to colleagues, with correspondence to Kraus interspersed. The letters are brief and informal in nature, discussing their families as well as professional concerns. The correspondence includes soliciting and offering opinions on equipment and supplies used in mineralogy studies, arranging to be at events, and correspondence between Kraus and his publishers. Later correspondence also includes letters related to administering his departments at the University of Michigan and to his church.
  - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1914, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (letters from Jennie Cooker)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1924, 35 folders (Box 1)
  - 1925-August1933, 41 folders (Box 2)
- Other Activities and Interests
  The Other Activities and Interests (1904-1970, 2.25 linear feet) is comprised of three subseries: Biographical, University of Michigan, and Other Organizations. Biographical provides an overview of his life, including articles, photographs and his diplomas. University of Michigan documents his career as a mineralogist and administrator, including his tenure as Dean of the Summer Session and his involvement with the Research Club. The subseries also includes speeches, articles, and a book written by Kraus, and his appointment books for most of his career that record his meetings and phone calls with colleagues and events he attended. The final subseries, Other Organizations, documents his religious involvement with the Ann Arbor First Methodist Episcopal Church and the Wesley Society and his involvement with the honors society Phi Kappa Phi. It also includes a history of the Mineralogical Society of America, of which he was a founding member and the first president.
  - Biographical
    - Account Books 1904-1907, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Activities through 1954 and Bibliography through 1962 (Box 3)
    - Base Lake Cottage (Box 3)
    - Biographical and genealogical materials (Box 3)
    - Correspondence to his family about trip to Europe 1926 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence to his family about trip to Europe 1936 (Box 3)
    - Diplomas and Certificates of Membership (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Box 3)
      (also in oversize Box 5)
    - Photograph Album, "Many Famous Scientists" (Box 3)
      (includes index)
    - Recognition for service to medical societies 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Kraus' student notebook (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan
    - Appointment Books 1925, 1928-1970 (Box 3)
    - Articles on mineralogy 1925-1930 (Box 3)
    - Committee to Consider Revision of University Calendar 1920-1926 (Box 3)
    - Carbide Patent Lawsuit Case 1909-1910 (Box 3)
    - Edward Orton Memorial Lecture 1954 (Box 3)
    - Foreign Students at the University of Michigan 1936-1944 (Box 3)
    - Gems and Gem Materials by Kraus and Holden, corrections for second edition, second impression (Box 3)
    - Henry Russel Lectures 1945 (Box 4)
    - Mineralogical Laboratory 1915-1933 (Box 4)
    - Research Club of the University of Michigan 1913-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Speeches and speech notes 1928-1961 (Box 4)
    - Summer Session Program 1917-1956, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Other Organizations
    - Ann Arbor First Methodist Episcopal Church
      - 1930-1932, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Search for minister 1934 (Box 4)
      - 1934-1938 (Box 4)
    - Mineralogical Society of America, "The American Mineralogist, Its First Four Years, and The Founding of the Mineralogical Society of America," 1969 (Box 4)
    - Phi Kappa Phi 1918-1940, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Wesley Foundation of the University of Michigan 1928-1938, 2 folders (Box 4)